<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>political science | Dirk Hovy</title>
    <link>https://dirkhovy.com/tags/political-science/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://dirkhovy.com/tags/political-science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>political science</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©  Dirk Hovy, 2026</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://dirkhovy.com/images/icon_huf5895639c94b85425f6a15eb3aa47208_32923_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>political science</title>
      <link>https://dirkhovy.com/tags/political-science/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Digital &#39;Echo Chambers&#39;: The Role of Viewpoint Diversity in Political Discussion</title>
      <link>https://dirkhovy.com/publication/2023-beyond-digital-echo-chambers-role-viewpoint-diversity-political-discussion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dirkhovy.com/publication/2023-beyond-digital-echo-chambers-role-viewpoint-diversity-political-discussion/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MiMac</title>
      <link>https://dirkhovy.com/project/mimac/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dirkhovy.com/project/mimac/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this inter-disciplinary project, Dirk Hovy and Tommaso Fornaciari team up with an international team of political scientists (led bt the University of Gothenburg) to develop mixed methods for analyzing political parties’ promises to voters during election campaigns. For democracy to function effectively, political parties must offer clear choices to voters during election campaigns. However, as parties’ communication with voters has become increasingly fragmented and targeted, it is much harder for citizens to keep track of what parties are promising. This threatens the quality of democratic representation. It also challenges established research methods for studying parties’ campaign promises. This project will develop new methods for studying parties’ promises in modern election campaigns. The project will integrate existing qualitative methods in political science and develop new research tools based on NLP. These AI-powered tools will enable researchers to examine parties’ campaign promises in large amounts of text and speech. The resulting research will be of significant benefit to citizens, who will receive greater clarity on the choices that parties are offering. These existing and new methods are highly relevant to research on text and speech in a wide range of social science fields. Until now, progress in this field has been stifled by limited dialogue among the proponents of different qualitative and quantitative methods. The project includes established experts on parties’ campaign promises, new media, qualitative and quantitative methods for analyzing political texts, and machine learning and natural language processing.
The project is funded by the Swedish 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rj.se/en/anslag/2019/mixed-methods-for-analyzing-political-parties-promises-to-voters-during-election-campaigns/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Riksbankens Jubileumsfond&lt;/a&gt; for 12M SEK.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twitter Healthy Conversations</title>
      <link>https://dirkhovy.com/project/twitterhealth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dirkhovy.com/project/twitterhealth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Echo chambers and online abuse are two significant problems affecting the health of conversations on social media. This interdisciplinary, multi-institutional project (led by George Washington University) helps Twitter tackle these issues by developing metrics and algorithms to measure various uncivil behaviors.
Given the concerns about growing polarization and the spread of misinformation, our first two metrics, mutual recognition and diversity of perspectives, will help Twitter diagnose issues that arise when users isolate themselves from those who hold differing opinions. Mutual recognition measures whether and to what extent people on opposing sides of an issue acknowledge and engage with rival claims. When recognition occurs, a public sphere is established. When there is no recognition, echo chambers result. Diversity of perspectives measures the range of claims made on the platform, how likely users are to encounter (as opposed to engaging with) divergent and unfamiliar claims, and how polarized the debate is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our second two metrics, incivility, and intolerance, will help Twitter identify and address abuse and targeted harassment. Incivility measures the presence of anti-normative intensity in conversation, including the use of profanity and vulgarity. However, recognizing that such anti-normative communication sometimes serves justifiable&amp;ndash;and in some cases, even beneficial&amp;ndash;ends, we distinguish this concept from intolerance. Targeted attacks on individuals or groups, particularly when carried out based on gender, sexuality, race, ethnicity, religion, or ability, threaten the fundamental democratic principles of equality and freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To classify these measures at scale, we draw upon existing work in various computational fields, notably natural language processing and network analysis, but take this work further in addressing the metrics outlined here. Moreover, beyond merely detecting and measuring mutual recognition, diversity of perspectives, incivility, and intolerance, we propose to study the effects these four phenomena have on users. In doing so, we offer a theoretically and empirically driven approach that will help Twitter diagnose the conversation&amp;rsquo;s relative health on its platform.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
